<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-09-17T12:47:43+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Bradley M. Davis</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Bradley Davis</name></author><entry><title type="html">Jazz au Chellah 2018</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/morocco/2018/09/15/jazz-au-chellah-2018.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jazz au Chellah 2018" /><published>2018-09-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-09-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/morocco/2018/09/15/jazz-au-chellah-2018</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/morocco/2018/09/15/jazz-au-chellah-2018.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/chellah2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Courtesy of Carlos ZGZ, Wikimedia Commons&quot; title=&quot;Ruins of Chellah; just outside Rabat, Morocco&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 23 years, the European Union and the Moroccan Ministry of Culture have jointly-hosted an international jazz festival at sites in historic medina of Rabat. The festival, now called Jazz au Chellah, lasts five days and is held in a 13th century fortified necropolis—a venue so cool, it was previously the site of both Phoenician and Roman trade centers. While Rabat holds a number of great cultural events every year, I think this one will be my favorite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the night I was able to attend, a Czech group named the AghaRTA Gang opened up with a performance entitled “There is Hope 2 !” Despite the name, the group played pretty tame but engaging music: fairly standard bebop with a saxophonist who knew his way around some Charlie Parker licks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highlight performance was the Steeve Laffont Trio with guest violinist Costel Nitescu, a jazz manouche/gypsy jazz group comprised of two guitarists and a bassist. These musicians were phenomenal, and the rare delight of hearing jazz manouche live was exciting. This form of folk music is normally upbeat and exciting, but Laffont’s compositions and the musicians’ skill really channeled the energy of &lt;em&gt;le Quintette du Hot Club de France&lt;/em&gt;. The stands were shaking as the audience clapped along, danced in their seats, and shouted in delight to every little Grappelli and Reinhardt allusion. For their penultimate song, the Trio played one of my absolute favorites: Les Feuilles Mortes (The Autumn Leaves). Between the perfect violin and guitar solos, I am doubtful Montand or Piaf could have performed much better. I would be tempted to say that all of the French in the audience would agree but as the applause was peaking, the musicians burst into Django Reinhardt’s Minor Swing and everyone went wild, clapping and stomping to the beat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/plugins/video.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2FJazzauChellah%2Fvideos%2F2147470535576089%2F&amp;amp;show_text=0&amp;amp;width=560&quot; width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; style=&quot;border:none;overflow:hidden&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final performance was a Moroccan duet with Abdelfettah Houssaini playing &lt;em&gt;oud&lt;/em&gt; and Driss Nigra playing a wide array of percussion and ambient instruments—including preparing, pouring, and drinking mint tea under a microphone. The &lt;em&gt;oud&lt;/em&gt;, or Arabic lute, is a predecessor to the Medieval lute and modern guitar. It is a beautiful instrument to hear, with construction and playing style as a sort of hybrid between violin and guitar. Given how much I love the &lt;em&gt;oud&lt;/em&gt;, how prevalent it is in Morocco, and my less-than-successful attempts to learn how to play it, I will certainly write more about it in the future. Throughout the performance, Houssaini demonstrated that he was a معلم (mu-ahlem), or master of the &lt;em&gt;oud&lt;/em&gt;. The skill of both musicians was best at show when Nigra stood behind Houssaini, embracing him and playing percussion on the &lt;em&gt;oud&lt;/em&gt; as Houssaini kept playing melody in what must have been the closest duet I have ever seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/oudduet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Abdelfettah Houssaini and Driss Nigra in Oud Duet courtesy of Festival Jazz au Chellah&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jazz au Chellah was quite the experience, and I hope that I stay in Morocco long enough to return and see all five days of the festival next year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/jazzauchellah2018.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Festival Poster and Lineup&quot; title=&quot;Jazz au Chellah Festival Poster and Lineup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images courtesy of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.m.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Chellah_%26_minaret,_Rabat.jpg&quot;&gt;Carlos ZGZ, Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://m.facebook.com/JazzauChellah/photos/a.2280325928657806/2280330111990721/?type=3&amp;amp;source=54&amp;amp;ref=page_internal&quot;&gt;Festival Jazz au Chellah&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Bradley Davis</name></author><category term="morocco" /><summary type="html">For 23 years, the European Union and the Moroccan Ministry of Culture have jointly-hosted an international jazz festival at sites in historic medina of Rabat. The festival, now called Jazz au Chellah, lasts five days and is held in a 13th century fortified necropolis—a venue so cool, it was previously the site of both Phoenician and Roman trade centers. While Rabat holds a number of great cultural events every year, I think this one will be my favorite.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Fulbright Program in Morocco</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/morocco/2018/09/05/fulbright-program-in-morocco.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fulbright Program in Morocco" /><published>2018-09-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-09-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/morocco/2018/09/05/fulbright-program-in-morocco</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/morocco/2018/09/05/fulbright-program-in-morocco.html">&lt;p&gt;The Fulbright Program is an international educational exchange established by Congress in 1946 in order to facilitate bilateral exchange throughout the world, with the first Morocco programs beginning in 1952. As &lt;a href=&quot;https://eca.state.gov/fulbright/about-fulbright/history/j-william-fulbright/j-william-fulbright-quotes&quot;&gt;described&lt;/a&gt; by Senator J. William Fulbright,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The Fulbright Program aims to bring a little more knowledge, a little more reason, and a little more compassion into world affairs and thereby increase the chance that nations will learn at last to live in peace and friendship.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fulbright grants are awarded to Americans and foreigners to fund university studies, original research programs, and teaching at all levels. However, individual awards take many forms. In my Moroccan cohort, there is a professor who will teach comparative religious studies and history of American religion courses in Arabic, a faculty researcher who is traveling between Spain, Morocco and Mongolia to research nomadic migration patterns, student researchers working on dissertations and theses on a wide-range of topics (e.g., development of post-colonial Moroccan literature, behaviors of Barbary macaques, rural solid waste programs), English Teaching Assistants (d.f., standalone professors within the context of the Moroccan university system), and a few other grantees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fulbright in Morocco is run by a binational commission, the Moroccan-American Commission for Educational and Cultural Exchange (&lt;a href=&quot;macece.org&quot;&gt;MACECE&lt;/a&gt;). Established in 1982, MACECE has helped over 2,400 grantees further their education in Morocco and the United States. Anyone interesting in applying to a Fulbright program should go to [us.fulbrightonline.org][https://us.fulbright.org] for more information.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Bradley Davis</name></author><category term="morocco" /><summary type="html">The Fulbright Program is an international educational exchange established by Congress in 1946 in order to facilitate bilateral exchange throughout the world, with the first Morocco programs beginning in 1952. As described by Senator J. William Fulbright, “The Fulbright Program aims to bring a little more knowledge, a little more reason, and a little more compassion into world affairs and thereby increase the chance that nations will learn at last to live in peace and friendship.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Campus Orthodoxies Strangle Healthy Discourse</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/04/20/campus-orthodoxies-strangle-healthy-discourse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Campus Orthodoxies Strangle Healthy Discourse" /><published>2018-04-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-04-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/04/20/campus-orthodoxies-strangle-healthy-discourse</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/04/20/campus-orthodoxies-strangle-healthy-discourse.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/trialofbradley.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Trial of Bradley&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students at Lewis &amp;amp; Clark have a strained connection to politics. They are much more aware of the world around them than the general public and even most college students. LC students are noble and empathetic in their concerns for discourse and the consequences of speech, but debates rarely take place. I often find myself wondering if the concern is earnest, or just performative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is no secret that LC skews liberal. There is a certain orthodoxy among students and professors — not quite a cohesive doctrine, but one that can certainly be defined by what it is not. The school cultivates this image, misguidedly focusing on the school’s politics rather than the liberal arts. What upperclassman can forget the school promoting photos of the anti-administration protests in 2015 on its Facebook page? The college co-opted this to demonstrate the administration’s progressiveness and willingness for dialogue, although then-president Glassner would not engage with protesters. For many underclassmen their first glance into campus life was a curation of how acceptable dissent is. But dissent from what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be ridiculous to think that any, let alone an appreciable number of, LC students would be in favor of violence. Perpetrating assault on any student, especially Tanguy Muvuna, would be an anathema to campus values. Nonetheless, students wanted to protest and so they did. Eventually, students raised some important concerns and the community is likely better for some of the conversations that ensued. But those who wanted to attend class to interrogate the problems or social structures of the day were stripped of an intellectual space to do so while protesters developed the very hierarchy they sought to critique. Organizers quickly became exclusive and began to shout down and shame students with different ideas for protest. Marginalized voices once again were ignored as students in positions of authority asserted their own, though ostensibly for the sake of others. Such behavior gnawed at the legitimacy of the protest and turned away sympathetic ears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granted, dissent is scarce in classrooms too. But this is not the fault of professors, many of whom seem to struggle to bring rigorous debate into the classroom. Rather, students stifle it on their own — afraid to overstep the imaginary bounds of acceptable opinion or to unintentionally offend a peer. They are afraid, it seems, of some illusory campus thought police. If such a thought seems hyperbolic, consider the dorm room whisperings between close friends recounting some idea that they did not want ridiculed or how pointless a roundabout discussion was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of this aversion may stem from concern of microaggression or other unanticipated consequence of speech, which is fine. We should strive to be respectful and diplomatic in speech. But the solution is not to speak in some sort of coded, ambiguous language. Be thoughtful in speech; if you make a mistake and cause offense then apologize and learn from being called-out, do not just be silent in class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have tried to break this pattern of frozen speech; sometimes succeeding, sometimes giving in to the pressure. My freshman year, I tried to start a College Republicans chapter. Not out of any particular conviction, as I grew up in a liberal California household, but more out of curiosity and a desire to push students to engage more deeply in political discussions at a time where we neither had a Young Democratic Socialist of America (YDSA) chapter nor a College Democrats chapter. I did not want to stir the pot into a frenzy but rather to develop a pretense for intellectual opposition on campus, and I proudly denied outside requests to bring gross polemicists on campus. But the group floundered; few were interested in collaborating with us and far fewer wanted to join with us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the memory lived on in a certain sense. I am still referred to as “the Republican” and have heard many insults because of this. I have since become friends with students shocked by the realization that they liked me. None of which is particularly surprising on this campus, but it should be shocking that students are discounted based on perception and not personal character or even belief. While the orthodoxy asserts that individuals are multifaceted, the groupthink often only recognizes one identity: the out-group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kudos to the few students or professors who act against the campus climate, often by running farther to the left. While I do not agree with the specific protests, I am happy to see them happening. Usually, posters that go up around campus or demonstrations that occur are trite to the point of absurdity. During Festival of Scholars, there are plans to join a national movement by holding a mass walkout as a statement against gun violence on the anniversary of the Columbine shooting. Perhaps, planners hope to shock the world by showing that LC students are generally in favor of gun restrictions and opposed to murder. Perhaps they prefer a symbolic gesture over interaction with student research on all types of issues. Like so many instances of LC activism, this appears to follow a trend rich in social capital rather than acting for meaningful change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, seldom have I heard more than an apathetic groan at the mention of our student government,  Associated Students of Lewis &amp;amp; Clark (ASLC). So few students engage with our student government despite its significant daily impact on campus life. It should be telling that there is rarely public attendance at Senate meetings, let alone a sufficient number of Senate candidates. The number of positions has been reduced twice in the past three years and still competition is minimal. But this sort of malaise seems to grow; each progressively older class is less involved. It should be striking that we did not have a contested ASLC presidential election, not even a rising senior looking for a resume boost. I cannot help but think that this lack of engagement is a result of broader trends on campus. Although ASLC is not particularly contentious, Senate debate is limited and few pieces of legislation garner dissent.How much have student needs or interests guided the ASLC?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I do agree with some sort of “marketplace of ideas” approach to campus speech, I am not advocating for any radical shift in discourse. I just want students to start having meaningful conversations on political and social topics. I believe that the lack of substantive or vocalized disagreement shapes our environment. For all of the great moments at symposia, how many students can say they have actually been intellectually challenged by a speaker? For all of the kind members of our community, how many reprehensible people have had their actions ignored because they stuck to the script, joined the right clubs and had people to vouch for their “wokeness”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The illusory nature of LC’s orthodoxy is certainly part of the problem. Usually, the latest talking points from John Oliver, the Atlantic or viral social media movement will suffice. We should think beyond what is in vogue and be excited by the prospect of challenging ourselves and our peers. Perhaps viewpoints will remain the same but at least they will be out of conviction. Beyond being important for our intellectual development, our discourse directly affects political and social campus life. We can do better and become thinkers, not just performers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This piece was originally published in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.piolog.com/2018/04/20/campus-orthodoxies-strangle-healthy-discourse/&quot;&gt;the Pioneer Log.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Bradley Davis</name></author><category term="Lewis&amp;Clark" /><category term="Progressivism" /><category term="Debate" /><category term="Education" /><summary type="html">Students at Lewis &amp;amp; Clark have a strained connection to politics. They are much more aware of the world around them than the general public and even most college students. LC students are noble and empathetic in their concerns for discourse and the consequences of speech, but debates rarely take place. I often find myself wondering if the concern is earnest, or just performative.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Entrepreneurship &amp;amp; Liberal Arts</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/02/02/entrepreneurship-and-liberal-arts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Entrepreneurship &amp; Liberal Arts" /><published>2018-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/02/02/entrepreneurship-and-liberal-arts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/02/02/entrepreneurship-and-liberal-arts.html">&lt;p&gt;I do not care for computer programming, accounting or business more broadly. As a political science major, I seek classes that read Plato or study Middle East relations. I have written in this paper about the need to encourage a Great Books curriculum. Nonetheless, I believe Lewis &amp;amp; Clark College’s most undervalued and underappreciated program is Entrepreneurial Innovation. In fact, I have seldom learned more than in Technologies of the Future — and certainly never had as much fun in class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Courses in Entrepreneurial Innovation (EINV) have been a source of confusion for students and frustration for faculty. Students are generally unaware of what the program is or what it offers; students walking past classes in session often wonder how they can play with robots for credit. Many professors have not hidden their distaste for the program: some are fearful of it creeping into their own departments, concerned with budget allocations or dismissive of classes perceived to lack academic rigor. While the robots are great, the other impressions need to change. As both a student and Teacher Assistant, I have been fortunate to see the true value of EINV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the more important program principles is teamwork — what some call radical collaboration.  As opposed to group projects in most classes, which are non-collaborative and unproductive as a rule, EINV classes combine students from a broad array of disciplines to create work that is representative of each individual’s interests and strengths. It is not uncommon to see students from social sciences, humanities and computer science use their majors to survey a market audience, develop an advertising campaign and build a product. However, EINV students are more likely to pursue and enjoy roles wholly unrelated to their field of study. This is far more instructive than a collaborative Google slideshow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly, many of the assigned projects are open-ended:     students are given a general objective but must define their own parameters, methods and project goals. Students learn how to problem solve in a meaningful way, in large part because they are responsible for identifying what problems they face. All of this provides a great crash-course in learning how to create an app or a startup, but it is just as instructive for academic work. Developing a business plan that outlines a target audience, market competition or product research is no different than writing a thesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Exploration &amp;amp; Discovery (E&amp;amp;D) does a good job of teaching students how to read and write en masse, neither the program nor most academic departments teach students how to think. Certainly, intellectual effort is required for succeeding in class and critical insight for academic work. But students should know how to efficiently brainstorm,  effectively discard drafts and confidently build on intellectual failures. By teaching these skills, entrepreneurship teach students how to think well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, EINV classes sometimes feel like playing in a sandbox: they allow for fun and creativity, but also teach how to shape one’s thoughts. Our education would be strengthened if E&amp;amp;D incorporated these aspects of EINV or advisors recommended these courses to their students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This piece was originally published in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.piolog.com/2018/02/02/einv-courses-have-value-but-are-largely-overlooked/&quot;&gt;the Pioneer Log.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Bradley Davis</name></author><category term="Lewis&amp;Clark" /><category term="Education" /><category term="Entrepreneurship" /><summary type="html">I do not care for computer programming, accounting or business more broadly. As a political science major, I seek classes that read Plato or study Middle East relations. I have written in this paper about the need to encourage a Great Books curriculum. Nonetheless, I believe Lewis &amp;amp; Clark College’s most undervalued and underappreciated program is Entrepreneurial Innovation. In fact, I have seldom learned more than in Technologies of the Future — and certainly never had as much fun in class.</summary></entry></feed>